Finding Aid for Houck, Kibler, and Smith families papers, 1853-2012
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Houck, Kibler, and Smith families papers
1853-2012
1910-1946
Kibler family.
2014144 Aa 2
Genealogical collection for the Houck, Kibler, and Smith families, whose ancestors settled Michigan between the 1840s and 1900s. Includes correspondence, estate records, diaries, photographs, scrapbooks, war records, and other materials.
5.0 linear feet
1 oversize boxes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Collection was donated by Roland and Jeanette Kibler (donor no. 10821 ) in three accessions in August 2012 and January 2013.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
The Houck, Kibler, and Smith families are long term residents of Michigan, settling in Lenawee and Monroe Counties between the late 1840s and early 1900s. Their ancestors settled from Ohio, Pennsylvania, New York, England, Germany, and Switzerland. Isaac Harvey Houck and Lydia Ella Lang were Michigan farmers who married in 1885. They gave birth to six children: Lolla Mae, William Jacob, Harvey Roy, Anna Ellen, Cecile Mae, and Ellen. Anna Ellen Houck later married Ralph Enos Smith in 1922. Ralph Smith was also a farmer while Anna was a school teacher. Ralph and Anna had two children: Mae Gene, a school teacher, and Lowell, a World War II Air Force veteran and business owner. In 1945, Mae Gene married Melvin D. Kibler, a World War II Army veteran, farmer, and electrician. Melvin Kibler was the son of George and Sadie Blanche Kibler, who are also represented in this collection.
This collection is organized by family unit and contains four series: Houck Family, Kibler Family, Smith Family, and Scrapbooks.
This genealogical collection traces the roots of three Michigan families. The papers include correspondence, estate records, visual materials, and war records.
Subjects:
Farmers--Michigan.; Houck family.; Kibler family.; Kibler, Blanche S., 1889-1962.; Kibler, George, 1876-1963.; Kibler, Mae Gene, 1923-2003.; Kibler, Melvin Dale, 1920-2012.; Lenawee County (Mich.)--History.; Monroe County (Mich.)--History.; Smith family.; Smith, Anna Ellen, 1899-1977.; Smith, Ralph Enos, 1896-1977.; Teachers--Michigan.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1939-1945.
Contributors:
Kibler, Blanche S., 1889-1962.; Kibler, George, 1876-1963.; Kibler, Mae Gene, 1923-2003.; Smith, Anna Ellen, 1899-1977.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Videotapes.
- Houck Family, 1858-1971
  The Houck Family series, 1858-1971 (0.2 linear feet plus folder in oversize box), organized topically, consists of correspondence, financial materials, photographs, and other materials primarily concerning Isaac Harvey, Lydia Ella, and Anna (Annie) Ellen Houck.
  - Autograph books and dinner dance invitation, 1879-1885 (Box 1)
  - Biographical information, 1946-1971 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and financial, 1886-1943 (Box 1)
  - Estate papers, 1942-1948 (Box 1)
  - Family photographs, 1858-1964; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Marriage certificate, 1885 (Box 6)
- Kibler Family, 1853-2012
  The Kibler Family series, 1853-2012 (1.2 linear feet), organized by family member, includes correspondence, photographs, and World War II materials. This series particularly documents the lives of Melvin and Mae Kibler, including correspondence, genealogical files, property records, and Mae Kibler's teaching records. The series also documents George and Blanche Kibler, including property records, estate records, and a secretary book for the Monroe County Civic League. The World War II material includes correspondence, discharge records, U.S. army materials, photographs, postcards, and uniform patches.
  - Melvin and Mae (Smith) Kibler, 1918-2012; 14 folders (Box 1)
  - Melvin D. Kibler, World War II, 1945-1946; 8 folders (Box 1)
  - George and Blanche Kibler, 1853-1963; 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Kibler family will and estate documents, 1941-1967 (Box 1)
  - Melvin and Mae (Smith) Kibler family photographs, circa 1870-1945; 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Kibler family farm (VHS), undated (Box 2)
  - Melvin and Mae (Smith) Kibler 50th anniversary guest book, March 25, 1995 (Box 2)
  - Andrew Becker Kibler scrapbook, December 11, 1981 (Box 2)
- Smith Family, 1859-1995
  The Smith Family series, 1859-1995 (3.6 linear feet plus folder in oversize box), organized by family member, primarily consists of genealogical materials and the records of Ralph and Anna (Houck) Smith. The records of Ralph and Anna include correspondence and property papers. The series also includes Anna's diaries and teaching records. Also included is a printed genealogy and family tree tracing the Smith family from 1585 through the 1980s.
  - Ralph and Anna (Houck) Smith, 1859-1975; 13 folders (Box 2)
  - Frank and Ralph Smith, 1882-1962 (Box 2)
  - Frank E. Smith estate, 1931-1934 (Box 2)
  - World War I, 1917-1920 (Box 2)
  - Lowell Smith, 1926-1949 (Box 3)
  - Anna (Houck) Smith, 1908-1975; 13 folders (Box 3)
  - Ralph Smith, June 1905 (Box 3)
  - Mae Gene Smith and Melvin Kibler 50th Anniversary Album, 1995 (Box 4)
  - Palmer (Smith) family Bible, 1852 (Box 4)
  - Walter Palmer of Charleston and Rehoboth, Massachusetts and Stonington, Connecticut: A 400-year (1585-1985) Family History (Box 4)
  - Ralph Smith (Palmer) maternal family tree, circa 1985 (Box 6)
- Scrapbooks, 1899-1973
  The Scrapbooks series, 1899-1973 (1.0 linear foot plus oversize box), includes several scrapbooks documenting all three families. This series includes two scrapbooks documenting military service in the Pacific during World War II.
  - Houck, Kibler, Smith family scrapbooks, circa 1899-1973; 4 volumes (Box 5)
  - World War II scrapbooks, 1945; 2 volumes (Box 5)
  - Mae (Smith) Kibler scrapbook, 1940-1944; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Melvin Kibler scrapbook, circa 1940 (Box 6)